Here we go. okay I see apple //e and we're ready to go
我们开始吧。这是Apple //e(Apple 2e) 一切就绪
all right so I wanted to do a very quick video maybe ten minutes or so
我想做一个非常简短的视频，大概十分钟左右
talking about programming like it's 1981
介绍一下1981年的编程方式
in particular, a lot of people seem to have questions about how exactly you would have programmed the Apple 2 back in the day
好像很多观众都特别想知道当时是如何在 Apple 2 上编程的
And I want to show you what it looked like before you had tools
我会先演示一下没有辅助工具之前的样子
Then I'll show you some of the very basic tools
之后再演示一些非常基本的工具
And then I'll show you maybe if we have time what an assembler looks like
如果有时间的话，我还会展示一下汇编器的样子
So here we've got our Apple 2e running an emulation, I'm gonna hit the reset button
这里已经启动了Apple 2e 的模拟器( Windows下可以用 AppleWin )，我将按下重置按钮
As if we have no no disc in the drive at all and here we are, we have no DOS
因为没有挂载磁盘，我们暂时看不到DOS界面
I can't look at anything, anything about anything all we have is the Apple soft basic interpreter which was built-in tool
什么事都干不了，目前只有苹果内置的基础解释器工具
so we could write a small basic program just like you'd expect to see.
如你所愿，我们可以写一个小的演示程序
The the basic program that everyone runs.
和每个人都会编写的基本程序一样，
That's not very interesting
没啥意思
sooner or later what everyone did on the Apple 2 of course was play games.
大家肯定会在 Apple 2 上玩游戏
some of those games had bugs and when the game crashed
部分游戏中有BUG，并且当游戏崩溃时
you would sometimes into basic if it were basic game.
如果它是BASIC游戏，有时可能会回到BASIC界面
but if it were written in machine language you might drop to an unfamiliar prompt and that prompt would look like an asterisk
但是如果它是用机器语言编写的，可能会出现一个不常见的星号提示符
in fact it will looked like this typically beep
实际上它长这样，显示时通常伴随着"哔"的声音。
and what is this prompt?Well, we can try and get some help
这个提示符有什么用？我们可以尝试获得一些帮助，
we got a beep. We could type help,H
发出了一个"哔"声，我们可以输入help和H
this is just like the VI editor if you're in UNIX
就像UNIX系统中的VI编辑器一样
what is this thing? Well,this is the Apple 2 machine language monitor.
这是Apple2 机器语言的监视器
So monitor means that you can inspect and change things in memory so let's try typing a number ok
这意味着你可以查看并修改内存中的值，所以先尝试输入一个数字
So that is literally the zeroeth byte in memory
实际上这是内存中的第0个字节
You can also do that
你也可以这么做
And we see that it contains the value 4C
可以看到它的值是4C
we can inspect other areas of memory we can go probably up to ffff.
我们可以查看内存中的其他区域，最大地址好像是ffff
which would be the probably that would actually be in the ROM memory opposed to the RAM
实际上在ROM而不是RAM中（FFFF存储IRQ/BRK中断的MSB）
we can inspect multiple bytes in memory by using the doc here, I can say show me all the memory there
可以用.的方式来一次查看内存中的多个字节
And if you've ever seen a hex dump
如果你之前用过hexdump
You might recognize this so this is showing us the first row is bytes 0 through 7
你可能会认出这个输出显示了第一行是第0到第7字节
and byte0 contains 4C byte1 contains 3C
字节0的值是4C，字节1的值是3C
so you know this is queue in all, but what can we actually do with it?
显示方式很好，但我们怎么操作它呢
Well, we can't just look at memory so there I'm looking at byte 800
我们不仅能观察内存值，以0800处的内存为例
And these all numbers here are hexadecimal by the way.
顺便说一下，这些数字在这里都是十六进制的
We can change them. I could say well instead of having 0, I want 800 to have this byte 99
我们还能修改它。比如将0800处字节的值从0改为99
And now if I look at it again I just changed memory.
再次查看0800，可以看到内存被修改了
I'm gonna poke a value into byte 640 here.
给地址为640的字节赋一个值
Up here, actually let me to use a better value I'm gonna poke value 55.
这里还是把620字节的值改为55更好
All right, you should see a blinking U up towards the top screen
您应该会在屏幕顶部看到一个闪烁的U
Where did it come from well let's do it again let's put that value on the same byte on memory
这是哪来的? 让我们重复一次，让我们把相同的值再次赋值给原来的位置
And there's another U
出现了另一个闪烁的U
so what just happened
发生了什么？
Well unlike today's modern machines which have what's called protected memory
不像现在的现代计算机有所谓的"受保护的内存"
on an 8-bit computer  like the Apple 2 you have complete access to all the memory in the system
在类似Apple2 这样的8位计算机上，你有权限访问系统中的所有内存
which means you can really hose yourself you could break things quite badly
这意味着你可能会让你心态爆炸或者把系统玩崩
but most devices would be what's called memory mapped to some region in memory
但大多数设备将内存映射到内存中的某个区域
so the text screen which is what we're looking at here is actually mapped from I want to say values
所以我们在这里看到的屏幕文本实际上是从
I want to say values from say 400 to 7ff,I think something like that.
可能是400到7ff的值，大概是这样
normally you would look this up if you want to know
通常情况，你需要去查一下具体的地址值。
when I changed byte 620 to 55, it poked that value that flashing U is the value 55
当我把620字节的值改为55时，那个闪烁的U就代表55这个值
That is 56 now. It's a flashing V
将值修改为56，现在就显示一个闪烁的V字母
If I say,let's do some multiple bytes.
如果我们修改多个字节的值
610 53 54 55 56 57 58 and there you could see the flashing STUVW
如果把610字节及其之后的内存值分别改为53 54 55 56 57 58，就可以看到闪烁的STUVW
All right so we can look at memory and we can change memory so what? What's the big deal?
我们可以查看和修改内存，你可能会觉得这没什么了不起的
Well the monitor actually does some more interesting things.
这个监视器实际上可以做一些更有趣的事情
in particular it can disassemble code
特别地，它可以执行反汇编操作
So let's look memory location 800 again which is a very common location for programs to begin
来看一下800内存地址处，这通常是程序开始执行的入口
and instead of just hitting return here, I'm going to add an L on the end
不要直接按回车，而是在末尾添加一个L
And now could see the monitor trying to disassemble the bytes that are in code as if they are 6502 machine language.
可以看到监视器试图反汇编代码中的这些字节（例如6502的机器语言）
now they might not actually be 6502 machine language
这些数据也许不一定是6502的机器代码，
Usually might be data just as I poked a value into the text
通常情况下可能只是普通的数据，就像我之前输入的值一样
Maybe this is just some data that happened you might be able to interpret it as 6502 assembly
只是因为解释器刚好能将这些数据当做6502的汇编代码来输出
but we can actually show this in action
让我们实际操作一下
so let's go ahead and write some assembly code in the monitor live
先在监视器里现场写一些汇编代码
so first I'm going to go ahead and clear this out
先把这些数据清理掉
just throw a bunch of zero zeros in there which should be interpreted as the instruction break
这里一大堆的 00 都被翻译为BRK指令
there's a faster way to do a region memory
有种更快的方法可以一次修改一段内存
I'll be honest it has been 30 years I don't quite remember
老实说我有点忘了，毕竟已经过去了30年
Now I could see we got a bunch of breaks here
可以看到这段内存都被显示为了BRK
so what you would do before you had tools,before you had an assembler
如果没有汇编程序和其他工具，你要怎么做呢
you get a notebook and you will probably have a quick reference card listing all of the op codes of the 6502 instruction set
你会拿到一本笔记本，还可能有一张速查卡，其中列出了6502指令集的操作码
and you would write your program in assembly language
然后使用汇编语言编写程序
kind of longhand what you think you would want to do on the left side of the paper
在一页的左侧位置上书写要实现的功能
and on the right side of the paper you would look up the opcode like you were looking up a logarithm with a slide rule
在同一页的右侧，先要查找操作码，就像在计算尺上查找对数一样
and you would write the opcode on the right-hand side
之后将操作码写在右侧
there are actually special pads of paper to help you do this
实际上，还有专门的帮助手册
because it was so such a common thing to do with 8-bit computers
因为当时8位计算机是非常普遍的
I'm going to write a useless program right now
现在来编写一个没有具体作用的程序
That just a couple lines of assembly code it doesn't do anything useful
只是几行没有具体功能的汇编代码
I have some programs that I have prepared for future ones of these but they don't want to go too long
我其实准备了一些后续的程序，但我不打算在这期视频中说太多
so let's go so the one opcode that is burned into my memory is a9 which stands for load the accumulator immediate mode
写入我的内存的一个操作码是A9，代表加载累加器立即数模式（LDA）
and you could take a value let's take 55
可以取一个值，比如55
And just say that and now if we look if we disassemble this code
如果我们看一下反汇编这段代码的结果
we can see the top line of the screen there it says a9 55 on the left and load the accumulator pound/dollar hex 55
在屏幕顶端我们可以看见左侧是A9 55 右侧是 LDA #$55（十六进制）
load the accumulator with the value 55
表示向累加器加载值0x55
let's also then add some more
让我们再增加一些数据 (40年后的苹果手机铃声)
let's try I can't remember it's 8D or 85 let's try an 8d
记不清是8D还是85了，先试下8D
40 06, I hope that's a vaild opcode,
...40 06 希望这是一个有效的操作码
I'm actually not using quick reference card right now so I'm kind of doing this kind of surfing here
我没有使用速查卡，只是随意浏览一下
alright so we can see that in memory location 802 we have stored the accumulator in memory location 64
好了，可以看到在802地址中的指令已经将累加器的值存储在640这个内存地址中
so let's go ahead and do some more load the accumulator with another value how about I don't know 42
继续向累加器载入值，比如42
and let's go ahead and just continue we can continue to type memory in here
可以继续在当前行输入值
we just poking values of memory and we'll store that in 41 06
这些值还是会写入之后的内存，我们将其存储在41 06地址中
these are byte swapped because of the endianness of the processor
这两个字节的先后顺序和实际值是相反的，原因是处理器的字节序（小端）
all right so now we have our four line assembly language program let's make it 5 lines and just finish it up with a break
我们的汇编程序现在有四行代码，再加一行BRK指令作为结尾
and so from the Apple 2 monitor you can run the program
然后就可以从Apple2监视器运行程序了
so let's go ahead and run the program
动手运行吧
Patrick in the chat says he now sees how I could stand to play things like Space Camp, yes exactly
聊天室里的Patrick说他现在能理解我为什么能忍受 Space Camp这种游戏了。的确如此。
so we're gonna say G, 800 G, go
用G来运行程序，例如800G
We just ran our progarm, it did't do much useful. when we ran it we got the status flags
我们运行了刚才的程序，它没什么具体作用，只是返回了一些状态标志
so this is showing us registers of the 6502 there are three registers
展示了6502的寄存器，先说前三个
the a is the accumulator the one register you can do arithmetic with, x and y are used for indexing generally for looping and pointer manipulation.
A是累加器，用于算术运算。X Y寄存器通常用于索引、循环和指针操作
P are the status flags
P是状态标志
which are a really complicated topic beyond today's talk
这是一个非常复杂的话题，今天就先不深入了
get into that next time if we get there and S is the stack pointer
下次有机会再说吧。S是堆栈指针。
You can see up here on the line labeled 814 it says 00 BRK and then a flashing u and a flashing b
可以在标记为814的行上看到，00 BRK，然后是闪烁的UB字符
that was the memory we just changed,we just poked the value into that memory
这就是我们刚才改变的内存位置，我们给它赋了个新值
now if I were to inspect that memory now those values wouldn't there
如果查看那段内存，那些值还没有保存到内存里
because I poked them into the text field or or the text view the text memory map and of course
因为我将它们输入到文本域或者叫文本视图映射的内存区域
here we are changing it so that we could see things
我们正在改变的就是映射的内存区域，所以才能看到修改
so that's the monitor at its most basic
这是就最基本的监视器功能
but we can do a little better and very quickly Apple did a little better
但我们还能做得更好，因为苹果很快就做了一点改进
they implemented something called the mini assembler.
他们实现了一个叫 mini汇编器 的程序
everyone knows about the monitor because sooner or later you crashed and ended up in it
每个人都知道监视器，因为迟早会由于程序崩溃而进入监视器界面
fewer people know about the mini-assembler
但很少人知道 mini汇编器
a mini-assembler helps you do what we just did but without having to look up the opcodes,hopefully.
mini汇编程序可以协助我们完成刚才的编程，免去查找操作码的麻烦
you enter the mini assembler
尝试进入mini汇编器
actually I think we won't able to do it here because I do load a disk
我觉得现在无法进入mini汇编器，因为我已经加载了一张磁盘
Oh look at that it's actually run because this is an apple 2e
哦其实运行成功了，因为我们现在用的是Apple 2e
so on an Apple 2 or plus you would have had to load a disk to do this but and we were able to do
如果用的是Apple 2 或者plus ,就需要加载磁盘。但我们现在可以直接开始
so let's see what happens here if we say...
让我们输入一些内容
great, so in case you missed what happened there I typed 800 :
补充一下，我刚才输入了800：
and then a9 99 like that and it immediately translated it into the opcode and kind of displayed results.
然后是A9 99，它立即将其翻译成操作码并显示出结果
so I think if I type a colon I can keep going. let's see if that's true
我觉得如果输入冒号，就可以继续操作后续的内存。试试对不对
let's try and store this in memory location 300
让我们看看是否正确，让我们尝试将其存储在地址为300的内存中
no it doesn't like that
不行
Oh, that's just a space,okay.
哦原来只要输入一个空格就好了
so then we're storing that 99 in memory location 300 let's continue let's load value 88
我们将0x99存储在地址为300的内存中，之后加载值88
and let's store let's transfer a to the X register
将a转移到X寄存器
and then let's store register in memory location 301 so I'm not that interesting you know
将X寄存器的值保存到地址为301的内存中，目前的操作还比较无趣
I believe we have to hit the reset button to leave the mini assembler
我觉得要按下“重置”按钮（模拟器中是Ctrl+F2）离开mini汇编器
We're looking our program there it is
这就是我们的程序了
we'll run our program first let's look at memory locations 300 and 301
在运行之前，先看下 300和301内存
they contain FF let's run our program
它们的值是FF。然后运行程序
And let's look at memory locations 300 301 again and you can see they contain 99 and 88
再次查看内存300 301，可以看到它们的值是99和88
the mini-assembler is really just a translator it's translating completely on the fly
mini汇编器实际上只是一个翻译程序，它可以动态翻译
you can type comments it won't keep them there's no file management here
可以输入注释，但汇编器不会保留注释，也没有文件管理功能
there just stuff is in and gone forever
要么写入，要么丢失
so to write a program at significant length if you're not laws
如果需要写代码量很多的大程序
you really need a program a real assembler that will have a nice editor will let you add comments
就需要一个真正的汇编器，包括支持注释的编辑器
have meta things so you could have variables
还要能支持元数据，这样就可以编写变量。
but this is the basics this is what you got if you bought an apple in 1978 before there was really any good software for it.
如果你在1978年买了一台苹果电脑，就只能用这些基础功能。当时还没有为其开发的优秀软件。
software for it this was the type of programming you could do
在当时，你只能这么编程
this was a leap above things like the KIM-1
但这已经是一次像KIM-1那样的飞跃了，因为
because you actually had a display on which you could see the op
因为它可以显示出操作代码
so that is the basic intro that I wanted to give
这些就是我想给出的基本介绍了
Not so much about how to programming assembly language because I think there's tons of resources about that
很少涉及汇编语言编程，因为这方面的资源已经很多了。
just the the feel of what it was like to try to do these things before tools existed
只是让大家感受一下在没有编程工具时如何编程
if I do another one of these I think the next step would be to load a assembler I would probably use.
如果有下一期的话，我打算加载一个我可能用到的汇编器
Merlin and show it
叫做Merlin 并展示它
should we should we save that till next time
要我现在演示吗?还是下次再说？（作者在Twitch直播）
I'm gonna go ahead and I'll do it now I might break the video here for YouTube
那继续吧，上传YouTube的内容可能就到此为止了
But just for the people who are watching I think
就当做直播观众的独家内容好了
let's just stick a disc in here and hopefully it will actually work.
插入磁盘，希望能用
I've like eight versions of Merlin
我大概有八个版本的Merlin
Waiting for it to load,
等待加载中
I have the emulator set to actual speed of an Apple 2 which is hideously slow of course
我把仿真程序的处理速度设置为Apple 2的实际速度，所以慢得离谱
so here we are in Merlin,you can see that there's various options here dealing with files let's just dive right in
这就是Merlin的界面了，可以看到这里有各种处理文件的选项，让我们深入一下
hit e to edit file we get more or less a line editor I'm
按e编辑文件，进入一个至少算得上行编辑器的程序
A to add a line okay we can tell it where we want our program to make it exactly
按a添加一行，增加程序入口
Let's make it exactly the same as the one we just did
写一个和刚才功能一样的程序
so we'll say ORG dollar 800
输入 空格 ORG $0800
this is not a 6502 opcode that's a hint to the assembler
这不是一个6502指令集的操作码，只是一个给汇编程序的提示符
we could also define some symbols so let's say head is equal to 0300, tail is equal to 0301
还可以自定义一些符号，比如head等于0300 tail等于0301
we can have comments this awesome program write some values
还能增加注释
And then we just write our code as as we'd like to
然后就按你自己的习惯写代码
the hardest part of doing this would actually be using a line editor like this
最难的部分其实是使用这样的行编辑器，这比写汇编更让人烦躁
full-screen editors we're all used to today
因为我们已经习惯了使用现代的全屏幕编辑器了
so I want to store this in memory location 300 so I'll just use the symbolic name i defined
我想把它保存在地址为300的内存中，所以使用自定义的符号名称
In fact I will say 88 whatever they say  transferred to the Y register this time
值为88，然后转移到寄存器Y
store Y in tail and then we'll finish up with a break
将寄存器Y的值存储在tail地址，然后用BRK结束这段代码。
Okay not a very interesting program but I want to stick with doing the same thing in different ways
不是个很有趣的程序，但我喜欢探索不同的方式
hey I hit return on an empty line here.
在空白行处换行
now I can assemble the program
这样就可以汇编代码了
In this case I happen to know because I read the documentation
因为我阅读过文档，所以我知道能这么做
the lack of online help by the way is a consistent feature of early Apple 2 programs
顺便提一句，缺少在线帮助是早期的Apple 2程序的一致特点
you simplely could not get anything done without the manual
没有手册就无法完成任何事情
The memory you had on the computer was so limited that the add-on online help system to most of programs
那时电脑上的内存非常有限，因此大多数程序都没有内置在线帮助功能
you wouldn't have room for your program
没有足够空间给你的程序使用
so let's go ahead and assemble it I'm answering no to that question
执行汇编，这个问题选择“否”
You could see bunch of op codes up here it kind of shows us what it looked like it mentions that we have a few symbols
可以看到上面有一堆操作码，展示了整个程序的样子，还显示了一些自定义符号
and then I think we want to quit so we can now save the source code.
现在应该退出，这样就可以保存源代码
let's just call it test program
文件名就叫TESTPROG
Is gonna save that as TESTPROG dot s s for assembly language we can then save the object code
这样就储存为TESTPROG.S，S代表汇编语言。接下来保存目标代码
Which is our actual program that we're going to run
这是我们将要实际运行的程序
hopefully this will work I'm going to quit out of the out of Merlin let's look at our disk
但愿能跑。我要退出Merlin了，让我们来看一下磁盘
A bunch of stuff here
一堆代码
Of course I save that right to the assembler disk which is not very cool
我把它直接保存在了汇编器的磁盘上，不是很讲究
let's just really quickly drop into the monitor make sure that the program is not in memory you can see it's not
返回监视器，确保程序不在内存中。可以看到它确实不在内存里
bunch of breaks so memory is empty and let's run our run we'll run it all at once
一堆BRK语句，所以内存是空的，让我们运行程序
just use brun we'll run it all at once what do they call it TESTPROG
用BRUN运行，它将一次运行所有名叫TESTPROG的程序
we can see the registers already look correct our program did what it was supposed to do
寄存器的值看起来是正确的，我们的程序实现了预期的功能
That's the long and short of it this is kind of what the tools looked like in 1978 to 1982
这些工具的优缺点如上所述。1978年到1982年的编程工具就是这样的。
and they got better over time you'll see that
随着时间的推移，工具越来越完善
If you pick up versions of Merlin from one of the Apple 2 disk archives you can see how it improves overtime
如果去对比Apple 2 disk archives 上不同版本的Merlin，就可以看到它是如何逐渐改进的。
eventually they got a real full screen editor instead of line editor
最终从行编辑器变成真正的全屏编辑器
but it's really a different world
这确实是两个截然不同的领域
and if I do another one of these I think the next one will be writing an actual program
如果再出一个类似的视频，我将会写一个实际的程序
and trying to one explain some of the vagaries at the 6502
尝试解释6502的一些变化
how programming even in assembly language is different on that CPU than on a let's say more full featured CPU
即使在汇编语言层面上，该CPU上的编程也不同于其他拥有更完善功能的CPU
and second I might try to motivate why would anyone put themselves through this
我还会试着让你感受当时的各种困难条件
and the one sentence answer is man the Apple 2 was really really slow
一言以蔽之 Apple 2 太慢了
and so any speed advantage you can get by directly an assembly language was super valuable
因此，任何通过直接的汇编编程带来的速度优势都是非常有价值的
we can go through an example next time
我们下次可以举一个例子来说明
that's it. thanks for tuning in
这就是本次全部内容了，感谢收看
and it's good taking this stroll down memory constrained lane with you, bye!
和各位一起在[内存受限的]小道上闲逛感觉很不错，我们下次再见！